- This is the President Wilson
Hotel in Geneva, Switzerland,
and outside of it, dozens
of Swiss policemen are getting
ready to arrest someone,
but the person they are about
to put in handcuffs is
not your typical tourist.
Instead, he's the son of one
of the most notorious
dictators in the world.
The police is about to arrest
the son of Muammar Gaddafi.
For over 40 years, the
Libyan ruler terrifies
and torments the world.
The vast majority of the wealth
of the country was siphoned
away into the pockets
of the Gaddafi regime.
His sons, this mad dog of
the Middle East has a a
goal of a world revolution.
And even though the policemen
know this isn't an ordinary
arrest, there is no way they
can predict the insane chain
of events that will be set
off by this causing a conflict
that would lead to economic warfare,
travel bans a hostage crisis,
and ultimately Gaddafi trying
to dissolve Switzerland
and divide it up among
its neighboring countries.
This is the story of
Gaddafi versus Switzerland.
Let's back up for a moment to understand
how we even got here.
It all started with a phone
call to the Swiss police in July
of 2008.
The call comes from a maid
working at the President Wilson
Hotel, located right on
the shores of Lake Geneva.
It is one of the most
luxurious hotels in the world.
It's Royal Penthouse Suite
is even considered the most
expensive hotel room on the planet, and
because of its location near
the United Nations building,
this hotel often hosts
international diplomats
and heads of state.
The maid tells the police that she called
because someone in distress approached her in the
hotel hallway.
This real hotel surveillance
footage shows that moment
the woman in distress
claims that she is working
for some very special hotel guests.
Hannibal Gaddafi and his
wife, Aline Skaf, the son
and daughter-in-law of Mummar
Gaddafi, who has ruled Libya
for nearly 40 years
At this point. Gaddafi is
a brutal dictator known
for crushing descent at home
and treating Libya like
his personal empire
and his children frequently
live it up in Europe.
Aline is currently eight months pregnant
and a couple had traveled
to Geneva in anticipation
of the birth of their
child, bringing along
with them many servants
to tend to their needs
with all the servants
and bodyguards, the Gaddafi's
had booked out a total
of 10 rooms at the hotel.
The surveillance footage
shows the corridor leading
to these rooms where a
makeshift table has been set up
with Libyan guards ensuring
that no unauthorized people can get access
to the dictator's son.
The woman asking for help
describes to the hotel mate
that she as well as one other employee
of the Gaddafi's have been brutally beaten
by the Gaddafi couple.
So after receiving the
phone call from the maid,
Swiss police enter the hotel
and they talk to the two employees
that claim to have been beaten.
They then take them both to the station
and there the full extent
of the abuse becomes clear.
As their many injuries are documented,
the two servants had
clearly been severely abused
and they feared that they
might even get killed once the
couple returns with them to Libya.
And so based on his evidence,
the Swiss police make the decision
to arrest Hannibal and Alene.
But this will not just be a simple arrest.
The police try to negotiate
with a delegate of the Gaddafi's
to convince Hannibal
and Alene to come to the
police station voluntarily.
But this doesn't work.
And after hours of talks, the
Geneva police decide it's time
for action leading to this
scene from the beginning
of the video with Swiss
police officers ready
to enter the hotel soon two
dozen police officers make it
to the floor with the Gaddafi suite,
but here they hit a problem.
Several bodyguards are
stationed outside the door
and they are determined to
prevent the police from entering.
The police. Officers try to argue
and convince the Libyan
bodyguards to give up,
but the bodyguards are
not willing to cooperate.
And so a clash breaks out
with police officers actively
fighting the bodyguards
of the Libyan ruling family.
After several tense moments of resistance,
the bodyguards are finally restrained
and two of them are arrested.
Finally, the way is now clear
to enter the Gaddafi suite
and Hannibal and Elene now surrender
and allow themselves to
be taken into custody.
They are discreetly
taken outta the back door
and drive away in unmarked cars in order
to protect their privacy.
Hannibal is taken to
the police station and
because Elene is so far
along in her pregnancy,
she is taken to a hospital.
It is a very delicate situation.
Normally visiting dignitaries
of foreign nations would
have diplomatic immunity
and they cannot be arrested.
But this doesn't apply if
the charges are criminal
and outside of the scope
of political interest,
like in this case with assault.
And besides being the
son of the Libyan leader,
Hannibal did not have diplomatic status in
Switzerland at the time.
And so Swiss officials
decide to move forward
with the assault charges.
Hannibal is treated just
as any other person charged
with a crime and once brought to jail,
he has his mugshot taken
while the couple is held for two days.
Their attorney is working for any solution
to try to get them out.
He tries arguing the courts
that the couple should at
least be allowed out on bail
and promises that the
Gaddafi's pose no flight risk
and surprisingly it works.
The couple is released on bail
for roughly half a million dollars.
It is an absurdly high amount,
but for the very wealthy Gaddafi family,
it is obviously not a problem.
Hannibal and Elene walk free out on bail,
and I don't really see how
this comes to a surprise
to anyone, but their first stop is
immediately to the airport.
Their bail has no travel restrictions,
and so the couple bought the first flight
straight back to Libya.
They have successfully
evaded prosecution once home.
The Gaddafi's reach an
undisclosed financial settlement
with the two servants who then agreed
to drop all charges against
Hannibal and a lien.
Now, normally you would think
that this would be the end
of the story, a bizarre
international incident in which the
Gaddafi's of course got away with it.
But actually this is just a beginning
because this incident has
made someone else really mad.
Muammar Gaddafi is outraged
once he hears about the
situation, especially
because Haal claims that he
was mistreated by the police
during the arrest, including
at one point having a bag
placed over his head.
And the Libyan leader now wants revenge.
Gaddafi demands to know the
names of the arresting officers,
but Swiss authorities deny his request,
and so he decides on a
scorched earth policy
with Switzerland severing any
ties until he gets those names
and an apology to his son.
He prohibits Swiss companies
from doing business in Libya
and closes offices of
several large companies.
He also cancels international flights.
Back then, Swiss International
Airlines used to fly
to Libya's Capital Tripoli
three times a week.
But on Gaddafi's order, those
flights are first reduced
to just one per week and
then completely prohibited.
And in an unprecedented move,
Libya a major supplier of oil
to many European countries,
completely cuts off crude
oil exports to Switzerland.
At the time, Libya
accounted for roughly 30%
of all Swiss oil imports, 2
million metric tons a year,
which Switzerland now has to
substitute from other places.
Gaddafi is clearly trying
to do whatever he can
to hurt Switzerland.
At one point he even withdraws
5 billion US dollars in
assets from his Swiss
bank accounts, $5 billion.
Just for context, the
entire GDP of Libya in
that same year was 60 billion,
and it is now when Gaddafi
also appeals to our nations.
In July of 2009, the G eight
summit was held in Italy
with Libya invited as a guest nation.
And while the other countries
were discussing major issues
like climate change
and energy policy, Gaddafi was trying
to convince fellow world leaders
to support his personal
vendetta against Switzerland.
His proposal was extraordinary.
Switzerland should be dissolved entirely
with the French speaking
regions handed to France,
the German speaking regions to Germany
and the Italian speaking ones to Italy.
The idea is quietly ignored
and so he submits his infamous
proposal again this time
to the United Nations
where it is quickly dismissed
As the UN charter prohibits
nations from threatening the
existence of other countries
and after achieving little
on the international stage,
Gaddafi has one different idea.
Up to this point,
the fallout had been mere
geopolitical disruptive,
sometimes costly, but abstract.
But what followed now was different
as two Swiss citizens completely
unrelated to the dispute,
got pulled into the conflict.
This is Max Gerdy and
this is Rashid Hamani.
They both hold Swiss citizenship
and they work for the company A, B, B.
Now, A BB is one of those
Swiss companies that was forced
to end its operations in
Libya following the arrest
of Hannibal, Goldie
and Hamani are arrested
and they are charged
with illegal residency
and illegal economic activity.
Even though when they
entered the country, none
of this was in place.
Just before he's taken
to prison, GDI manages
to briefly call the
Swiss embassy for advice
because he knows he hasn't
committed any crime,
but there is little any
ambassador can do for the two men.
The Libyan officers are
officials of the government
and there is no grounds for GDI
and Hamani to resist being arrested.
And so the two men are taken
to prison where they are held
with no idea what is coming next.
After 10 days with no
additional information,
they are finally allowed out on bail,
but the condition of
their bail prohibit them
from leaving the country.
Their passports are confiscated
and they remain stuck in Libya while their
charges are pending.
Meanwhile, back in Switzerland,
Swiss authorities are aware
of the arrested men
and begin work immediately
to bring them back home.
Ambassadors try negotiating
with Libian officials,
but they make little progress also
because Gaddafi denies that
these arrests are in retaliation
for his son being arrested.
And with diplomacy failing
Swiss authorities begin to turn
to an extraordinary new
approach using special forces
to smuggle the two men out of Libya.
And the plan is to go like this.
South of the city of
Chipotle, there is a compound
of buildings that belongs
to the Swedish telecommunications
company, Ericsson.
And on their property there is
a large swimming pool as well
as a tennis court.
The plan is that girlie and
Hamani will visit that building.
Their cover will be that
they are simply going there
to relax and use the pool.
And so the men make it a habit
to frequently drive from the
Swiss embassy all the way to
that swimming pool compound,
spend the day there
and then head back to the embassy.
This way the Libyan officials
secretly shadowing them will
become used to that movement
and hopefully they will
pay less attention.
Now the plan is that on one
random day, instead of heading
to the pool, there will be
a driver waiting for them
so they can secretly
sneak into an escape car
and this car will then take
them through the desert
and across the border leaving the country.
But this plan has its weaknesses for one,
even if they make it to Egypt, Algeria
or Tunisia, all those countries
at the time had good ties
with Libya and were very likely
to simply send the men straight back.
And so eventually the plan gets scrapped,
but a new plan is drawn
up by Swiss intelligence,
this one even more adventurous.
Instead of going to a
swimming pool, girlie
and hamani would be
provided with jet skis.
Then in the middle of the night
they could head to the beach
and take their jet skis out
to the Mediterranean sea.
Once they are out on the water,
they would just keep
going towards the horizon
for exactly 12 nautical miles
because at 12 nautical miles
the territorial waters of Libya
and here special forces with
boats will be waiting for them
and pick them up off the jet skis.
From here on, they can
safely head towards Italy.
But as fascinating as all of
these escape plans are, none
of them ever receives the
green light most likely
because they're deemed too risky.
And instead, Swiss authorities
once again turn to diplomacy.
We opening negotiations with the dictator.
By this point, it had been
over a year since Hamani
and GDI were arrested, and
in an unprecedented move,
the president of Switzerland,
Hans Mads, decides to travel
to Tripoli himself in order
to broker their release
and restore normal relations
between the two countries.
Mez knows that bowing
to a dictator will be an unpopular move,
but he's still determined
to try for the sake
of getting Hamani and girly home.
Even still, he's careful with his words.
Gaddafi wants an apology
for the arrest of his son,
and Merz decides to finally give him one
and publicly agrees that the arrest
of the dictator's son was unnecessary
and the Swiss president decides
to go even another stepfather.
Madz knows that Gaddafi wants
the names of the officers
who arrested his son.
Matts also knows that he can't
really give up those names,
but he does promise
to at least establish
an independent tribunal
that will investigate if Hannibal was
mistreated during his arrest.
And it is starting to
look better as in return
to these concessions.
The Libyan Prime Minister
promises that GDI
and Hamani will be allowed
to leave Libya within a few weeks.
It is the best that Merz seems to be able
to get from the Libyan officials.
And so he returns home
though instead of applause
for arranging the hostages
release, he returns to scorn
and criticism over the
apology with many claiming
that it will do little good.
And those that are doubting
seem to have a point,
especially once a new wrinkle
appears in the already
troubled Swiss Libyan relations
Tribune De Janene,
a newspaper based in Geneva
leaks the mugshot that was taken
of Hannibal Gaddafi after his arrest.
This is a new step of
humiliation for Hannibal
and the Gaddafi family as a whole.
The Gaddafi's immediately
file a civil suit against a
newspaper seeking the equivalent
of 90,000 US dollars in damages.
And a Swiss court does rule
that ALT's privacy was indeed
violated by the leaked photos,
but it denies awarding the Gaddafi any
monetary compensation.
But if the arrest of GDI
and Hamani is not retaliation
for Hannibal's ongoing situation,
this new development should
not affect the upcoming
release of the two men.
And at first it does seem
that everything is still
on track just three days
before they are to board a
plane for Switzerland, GDI
and Hamani are sent to a liven
doctor for a final checkup
to make sure they are in good health.
But once they go into the hospital,
they never come back out.
Gdi and Hamani have simply vanished,
fearing the worst Swiss diplomats
begin searching everywhere
for the two men not knowing
if they are even still alive.
Weeks pass.
And Libyan officials
eventually declared that Goldie
and Hamdani are held at a
secure location, secure from
what Swiss officials don't know,
but at least it seems to be confirmation
that the men are still alive
and is at this point when
the strategy seems to change.
Instead of causing up to the Gaddafi
and trying to find some
compromise in negotiations,
Switzerland decides
to put pressure on
Libyan officials in a way
that they know will hurt.
They begin to deny issuing
visas to top Libyan officials
for Chenin zone, including
to the Gaddafi family
as part of the Sheen agreement.
If one country that is part
of this agreement has blacklisted
anyone from entering all
countries must comply.
And this effectively bars the
entire Gaddafi family from
entering nearly all of Europe.
Just days after this
announcement, out of nowhere,
a car pulls up to the
Swiss embassy in Tripoli
and out tumble non-ED and Girly
and Hamani released from
wherever they were held
for seven weeks.
Though Libyan officials had
denied they were being held
captive, the men would later report
that they had been held in
solitary confinement in prison
cells with no information
provided to them as to what was going on
with the two men safely
secured inside the embassy.
They are now confined
within the building for fear
that should they leave, they
could be kidnapped again.
It is totally unclear
how they can safely get
back to Switzerland.
Goldie and Hamani are in safety,
but the relations between Libya
and Europe are now at
their absolute lowest.
Gaddafi announces
that Libya will impose its
own travel ban declining
to issue visas for any
EU citizens to Libya.
And now suddenly the European
Union is involved in the
conflict whether it wants to be or not.
Many countries are outraged,
especially countries like Italy,
which have a large economic
interest in being on good terms.
With Libya, with pressure from the eu,
mounting Switzerland agrees to
lift the Shang and travel ban
and in return, Libya also agrees
to lift its own ban on EU citizens,
but Libya still refuses to allow Gdy
and Hamdani to return to Switzerland.
Instead, the two men must
now finally face trial
for their charges still
confined to the Swiss embassy.
GDI and Hamani do not appear
in court when the Libyan judge
returns their convictions.
The verdict, both men are to
serve 16 month prison sentences
for their alleged visa and
business activity crimes.
Goldie and Hamani refused to
leave the embassy to report
to prison, and their lawyers work
to appeal their conviction.
And amazingly it works to a degree.
Hamani has his sentence
vacated completely,
and Goldie has his sentence
reduced from 16 months
to four along with an imposed fine.
Still, he is not willing
to serve his sentence in a Libyan prison
and the situation heats up.
Once again. Libyan officials demand
that Goy surrenders himself
to serve his sentence
and to add even more
pressure to the situation.
The Libyan police begin
surrounding the embassy threatening
to break in and storm the building.
If Goldie doesn't surrender in preparation
for a possible attack,
Swiss diplomats begin burning
all confidential documents so
that they cannot be stolen.
And they turn to Swiss authorities
back home for advice on
what to do and are told that
the decision remains with them.
And so Girlie makes a difficult
and painful decision
seeing no other way out.
He decides to step outside the building
and allow Libyan authorities to arrest him
and take him to jail, hoping
that just serving his
four months sentence,
he may finally be allowed to return home.
After all, with gdi secured
with the Libyans, Hamani can
now examine his own situation.
And since his charges have been cleared,
he's finally allowed to leave Libya.
But with one final stipulation,
he must read a pre-written
statement condemning Switzerland
for how they handled the
situation, forcing him
to be imprisoned in their embassy
and praising the Libyans
for taking care of him.
It is a price Hamani is willing to pay
to finally be allowed to leave.
And after making the statement,
Hamani is whisked away
by car and driven to neighboring
Tunisia with no issue.
Hamani is finally free.
Goldie, on the other hand, has
been taken to a Libyan prison
where he begins his four months sentence.
And this is where in
a truly bizarre twist,
things came full circle.
As one day during his time in prison,
GDY is suddenly summoned
to briefly leave his cell.
That is because someone
would like to speak with him
and that somebody is none of
than Hannibal Gaddafi himself.
The man who's arrest in
Switzerland has caused this whole
drama to begin with, now
wants to meet Max Goldie
In a televised interview,
Hannibal speaks with Goldie
and he allows girlie to call his mother
to wish her a happy birthday.
In return, GDY expresses
sympathy to Hannibal
for his arrest.
Back in Switzerland though,
Hannibal gets the theatrical
show of an apology
for his arrest from Goldie.
It doesn't sway him to Grant
Goldie an early release.
Goldie returns to his
cell serving out the rest
of his four months sentence.
As the end of the four
months is approaching,
Swiss diplomats travel
to triple E to ensure
that girlie will be released.
And after almost two
years since it all began,
girlie can finally return home.
And as girlie steps off
the plane in Switzerland,
welcomed home by his family
and the diplomats that fought
so hard to get him back,
he vows to never again return to Libya.
Now, all of this happened
between July of 2008
and June of 2010,
but what no one could have
predicted at this point is
that the reign of Gaddafi
in Libya was about
to come to an end.
Just half a year
after the release of GDI protests
started to erupt in Libya.
Eventually a civil war broke out
and the gaddafi's were ousted from power.
It ended the 42 year long
rule of more Mark Gaddafi,
a time period with dozens
of fascinating stories.
My creator, friend, real life Lore,
has recently made a dedicated
episode about Gaddafi telling
the crazy stories of his rain
and of his eventual downfall.
And I can truly recommend this episode
and the entire series, Matt
King's, that it is a part of
his documentary series
covers the most insane
and eccentric rulers, dictators,
and kings of the modern era, from Gaddafi
to the North Korean leaders,
and even an entire episode
about Uday Hussein.
Now, this series is exclusive to Nebula,
which is a streaming service where me
and a bunch of other
creators get to make videos
with full creative freedom.
To give you an example, this
story you just watched about
the feud between Libya
and Switzerland did not
include significant violence.
So it was perfectly suited for YouTube.
But certain subject matters such
as the topics discussed in Matt
Kings would just not work on
this platform because these
videos would be demonetized.
It's also why I created
my own Nebula original
series under Exposure.
And in it I often discuss
darker subject matters.
For example, one of my
most watched videos,
there is an episode where I
mapped out what exactly happened
during the rate on the Bin
Laden compound in 2011.
And besides that, since Nebula
is a subscription service,
it also means that we creators get
to make more elaborate projects.
And of course, it's
completely free of any ads.
So if you want to check
out what I think are some
of the most innovative and
creative projects on the internet
right now, then go to Nebula tv slash Neo.
And if you use exactly this link,
you're not only supporting my show,
but you're also getting the
best deal on Nebula, 50%
of an annual subscription,
which translates
to 30 bucks a year.
And thank you so much
for watching this video.